Guide to the Hendricks Family Papers, 1713-1976 (bulk 1755-1959) MS 295
New-York Historical Society
- Series IX. Hendricks and Related Families Supplement (1790-1976), 201743; 3.77 Linear feet (10 boxes)
  - Subseries IX.C. Henry Solomon Hendricks, 201746
    This subseries includes Henry's general correspondence (1895-1958) and travel diaries (1901, 1914), as well as papers relating to his time as ensign in the United States Navy (1917-1918) and United States Coast Guard Reserve and Auxiliary.
    The bulk of the subseries contains files from his roles as trustee and president of Congregation Shearith Israel (1919-1953).
    The material in Subseries IX.C is arranged chronologically by format, with general correspondence and travel diaries preceding military papers, and Congregation Shearith Israel files following.
    - Correspondence: general, 1895–1931 September; 201784 (Box 23, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence: general, 1931 October–1947 March; 201785 (Box 23, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence: general, 1947 May–1958; 201786 (Box 23, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence: Congregation Shearith Israel donations, 1925–1944; 201787 (Box 23, Folder 4)
    - Biographical information and obituaries, 1953–1959; 201788 (Box 23, Folder 5)
    - Notes and ephemera, 201789 (Box 23, Folder 6)
    - Travel diary, 1901; 201790 (Box 23, Folder 7)
    - Travel diary, 1914; 201791 (Box 23, Folder 8)
    - Navy papers, 1917–1939; 201792 (Box 23, Folder 9)
    - Navy identification tags (3 items), n.d.; 201793 (Box 23, Folder 10)
    - U.S. Coast Guard Reserve & Auxiliary papers, 1941–1948; 201794 (Box 23, Folder 11)
    - Congregation Shearith Israel files, 1916, 1919–1923; 201795 (Box 24, Folder 1)
      Includes a letter from Rabbi H. Pereira Mendes on the prohibition of dancing in the synagogue basement, 19 January 1920.
    - Congregation Shearith Israel files, 1924–1926; 201796 (Box 24, Folder 2)
    - Congregation Shearith Israel files, 1927; 201797 (Box 24, Folder 3)
    - Congregation Shearith Israel files, 1928–1929; 201798 (Box 24, Folder 4)
    - Congregation Shearith Israel files, 1930–1931; 201799 (Box 24, Folder 5)
    - Congregation Shearith Israel files, 1932–1934; 201800 (Box 24, Folder 6)
    - Congregation Shearith Israel files, 1935–1937, 1939, 1941; 201801 (Box 24, Folder 7)
    - Congregation Shearith Israel files, 1946–1948; 201802 (Box 25, Folder 1)
    - Congregation Shearith Israel financial reports, 1945–1953; 201803 (Box 25, Folder 2)
    - Congregation Shearith Israel, 70th Street Holding Corporation reports, 1946–1949; 201804 (Box 25, Folder 3)
  - Subseries IX.D. Rosalie Gomez (Nathan) Hendricks, 201747
    Rosalie Gomez (Nathan) Hendricks (1894-1986) was the daughter of Edgar J. Nathan Sr. and Sara (Solis) Nathan [see Subseries IX.G], and the wife of Henry Solomon Hendricks [see Subseries IX.C]. She donated the original Hendricks Papers to the New-York Historical Society in 1965. This subseries includes her personal correspondence, genealogical research, miscellaneous notes and speeches.
    The material is sorted chronologically by format.
    - Correspondence: general, 1916–1940; 201805 (Box 25, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence: general, 1946–1967; 201806 (Box 25, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence re: portrait of Gershom Mendes Seixas commissioned for Columbia University, 1929–1930; 201807 (Box 25, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence and papers re: donation of Hendricks Family Papers to New-York Historical Society, 1954–1976; 201808 (Box 25, Folder 7)
    - Addresses, articles, notes, speeches, 1927–1967; 201809 (Box 25, Folder 8)
    - Genealogical material on Gomez, Hendricks, Levy, Nathan, Seixas, and related families, 201810 (Box 25, Folder 9)
    - Genealogical material on the link(s) between poet Emma Lazarus (1849–1887) and the Nathan family, 201811 (Box 26, Folder 1)
    - Research and article on Rebecca Gratz (1781–1869), 1881-1933; 201812 (Box 26, Folder 2)
      Includes Rosalie (Nathan) Hendricks's "Jewish Daughters of the American Revolution," Women's League Outlook, vol. 3, no. 4 (May 1933), 2.
    - Henrietta Szold research: correspondence, 1897–1938; 201813 (Box 26, Folder 3)
    - Henrietta Szold research: printed material, 1892–1945; 201814 (Box 26, Folder 4)
    - Scrapbook, 1954–1956; 201815 (Box 26, Folder 5)
      Focused on tercentenary celebrations of Congregation Shearith Israel.
    - Scrapbook, 1957–1959; 201816 (Box 26, Folder 6)
    - Ephemera, 1902–1927, n.d.; 201817 (Box 26, Folder 7)
    - Photographs, n.d.; 201818 (Box 26, Folder 8)
      Includes exterior and interior views of Congregation Shearith Israel, Central Park West and West 70th Street.
  - Subseries IX.E. Hays and Solis families, 201748
    This subseries contains miscellaneous papers and genealogical material relating to the intermarried Hays and Solis families, from whom Rosalie Gomez (Nathan) Hendricks [see Subseries IX.D] descended.
    Hays family material precedes Solis family material. Each folder is sorted chronologically.
    - Esther Ellen (—?—) Hays: linen swatches, n.d.; 201819 (Box 26, Folder 9)
      Wife of David Hays.
    - David Hays Solis (1822–1882): obituary, 201820 (Box 26, Folder 10)
      Husband of Elvira (Nathan) Solis (1826-1912).
    - Elvira (Nathan) Solis (1826–1912) [mother]: miscellaneous papers, 1852–1912; 201821 (Box 26, Folder 11)
      Wife of David Hays Solis (1822-1882).
    - Elvira Nathan Solis (1860s–1953) [daughter]: correspondence, 1892–1913; 201822 (Box 26, Folder 12)
      Daughter of David Hays and Elivra (Nathan) Solis.
    - Solomon Solis-Cohen (1857–1948): printed material, 1902, 1911–1912; 201824 (Box 27, Folder 1)
      Husband of Emily Grace (Solis) Solis-Cohen.
      Missing Title
      A System of Physiologic Therapeutics (1902)
      The Relation of the Pharmacopoeia to the Practice of Medicine (1911) [version published in Bulletin of the American Pharmaceutical Association (September 1911)]
      The Relation of the Pharmacopoeia to the Practice of Medicine (1911)
      "Some Useful Household Medicaments," New York Medical Journal (17 February 1912)
      Brief Notes on Vasomotor Ataxia (1912)
      "Love Called Me Not Away" [poem; undated typescript]
    - Emily Grace (Solis) Solis-Cohen (1859–1936): poems (2 items), 1910, n.d.; 201823 (Box 27, Folder 2)
      Daughter of David Hays and Elvira (Nathan) Solis; wife of Dr. Solomon Solis-Cohen.
    - Emily Solis-Cohen Jr. [born Emily Elvira Solis-Cohen] (1886–1969): miscellaneous papers, 1915, 1932; 201825 (Box 27, Folder 3)
      Daughter of Solomon and Emily Grace (Solis) Solis-Cohen.
    - Isaac N. Solis (1857–1909): correspondence, 1890–1909; 201826 (Box 27, Folder 4)
      Son of David Hays and Elvira (Nathan) Solis.
    - Isaac N. Solis (1857–1909): obituaries (2 folders), 201827 (Box 27, Folder 5-6)
  - Subseries IX.F. Nathan family, 201749
    This subseries contains miscellaneous papers and genealogical material relating to the Nathan family, from which Rosalie Gomez (Nathan) Hendricks [see Subseries IX.D] descended.
    Material is sorted chronologically.
    - Letter to Seixas Nathan[?]., 1821 October 1; 201828 (Box 27, Folder 7)
    - Gershom Nathan (1821–1864): Diary, 1843; 201829 (Box 27, Folder 8)
      Son of Seixas and Sarah (Seixas) Nathan; husband of Rosalie (Gomez) Nathan.
    - Gershom Nathan (1821–1864): Diaries, 1858, 1860; 201830 (Box 27, Folder 9)
    - Gershom Nathan (1821–1864): Papers, various; 201831 (Box 27, Folder 10)
    - Rosalie (Gomez) Nathan (1825–1890): Correspondence, valentines, 1840s-1870; 201832 (Box 28, Folder 1)
      Daughter of Aaron Lopez and Esther (Hendricks) Gomez; wife of Gershom Nathan.
    - Clarence Seixas Nathan (1856–1924): Genealogical and biographical material, 1910–1924; 201833 (Box 28, Folder 2)
      Son of Gershom and Rosalie (Gomez) Nathan; husband of Esther (Solis) Nathan.
    - Esther (Solis) Nathan (d. 1950): Genealogical and biographical material, 1903–1950; 201834 (Box 28, Folder 3)
      Daughter of David Hays and Elvira (Nathan) Solis; wife of Clarence Seixas Nathan.
    - Frederick Nathan (1844–1918): Memorial, 201835 (Box 28, Folder 4)
      Son of Benjamin and Emily G. (Hendricks) Nathan; husband of Maud (Nathan) Nathan.
    - Maud (Nathan) Nathan (1862-1946): Working Women and the Ballot [pamphlet], circa 1910; 201836 (Box 28, Folder 5)
      Wife of Frederick Nathan.
    - Frances Nathan (1863–?): Correspondence, 1904–1924; 201837 (Box 28, Folder 6)
      Includes a rejection letter from famed theatrical producer David Belasco (1853–1931), 12 January 1904.
  - Subseries IX.G. Edgar Joshua Nathan Sr. and family, 201750
    Edgar Joshua Nathan Sr. (1860-1929) was the son of Gershom and Rosalie (Gomez) Nathan. He was the husband of Sara (Solis) Nathan and father of Rosalie Gomez (Nathan) Hendricks and Edgar Joshua Nathan Jr. Edgar Sr. was an attorney active in legal and philanthropic organizations, as well as Congregation Shearith Israel. Most of this subseries is comprised of condolence letters sent to his family and law partner on his death in 1929.
    The material is sorted chronologically.
    - Correspondence and papers, 1887–1925; 201838 (Box 28, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence and papers re: Cyrus L. Sulzberger campaign, 1903; 201839 (Box 28, Folder 8)
      Cyrus Leo Sulzberger (1858-1932) was the unsuccessful Fusion Party candidate for Manhattan Borough President in 1903.
    - Miscellaneous papers, n.d.; 201840 (Box 28, Folder 9)
    - Condolence letters, 1929 June 18–21; 201841 (Box 28, Folder 10)
    - Condolence letters, 1929 June 22–[December?], n.d.; 201842 (Box 28, Folder 11)
    - Condolence telegrams, 1929 June–July; 201843 (Box 29, Folder 1)
    - Condolence letters sent to law partner, Michael H. Cardozo, 1929 June 18–22; 201844 (Box 29, Folder 2)
    - Condolence list, [1929]; 201845 (Box 29, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence re: establishment of a Jewish Theological Seminary scholarship in his honor, 1929–1930; 201846 (Box 29, Folder 4)
    - Obituaries and memorials, 1929; 201847 (Box 29, Folder 5)
    - Edgar Joshua and Sara (Solis) Nathan Sr.: marriage invitation, 1890 June 4; 201848 (Box 29, Folder 6)
    - Sara (Solis) Nathan (d. 1937): Obituaries, 201849 (Box 29, Folder 7)
      Daughter of David Hays and Elvira (Nathan) Solis; wife of Edgar Joshua Nathan Sr.; mother of Rosalie Gomez (Nathan) Hendricks and Edgar Joshua Nathan Jr.
    - Edgar Joshua Nathan Jr. (1891–1965): Correspondence and obituaries, 1937, 1953, 1965; 201850 (Box 29, Folder 8)
      Son of Edgar Joshua Nathan Sr. and Sara (Solis) Nathan. Edgar Jr. was Manhattan Borough President, 1942-1945.
  - Subseries IX.H. Printed material, 201751
    This subseries includes published pamphlets, periodicals, and books on Jewish life and religion, politics, biography, and social services.
    The material is divided by topic and/or publishing body (e.g., Jewish Theological Seminary) and then arranged chronologically. Note that the newspaper clippings in box 31, folders 3-4 are too brittle for use.
    - American Jewish Historical Society meeting notices and programs, 1892–1903; 201752 (Box 29, Folder 9)
    - Jewish Theological Seminary publications (folder 1 of 3), 1908-1936; 201753 (Box 29, Folder 10)
      List of Members (1 February 1908)
      S. Schechter, Abraham Lincoln (1909)
      Louis Finkelstein, The Pharisees: Their Origin and Their Philosophy (1929)
      Dedication of New Buildings Programme (1930)
      Herbert H. Lehman, The Problems of Present Day Civilization (1936)
    - Jewish Theological Seminary publications (folder 2 of 3), 1937; 201928 (Box 29, Folder 11)
      James Bryant Conant, Learning's Necessity for an Able Minister (1937) [2 copies]
      Cyrus Adler, The Semi-Centennial of the Seminary (1937)
      Louis Finkelstein, Tradition in the Making: The Seminary's Interpretation of Judaism (1937)
    - Jewish Theological Seminary publications (folder 3 of 3), 1937-1940; 201929 (Box 29, Folder 12)
      Heritage: 1887, 1937, 1987 (1937)
      Arthur H. Compton, The Religion of a Scientist (1938)
      Cyrus Adler: Addresses by Professor Louis Ginzberg, Sol M. Stroock, Esq., Professor Louis Finkelstein (1940)
    - Jewish institutions and social services, 1926–1955; 201754 (Box 29, Folder 13)
      Jewish Family Service of New York, 80 Years: A Report (ca. 1955)
      Fifty Years of Social Service: The History of the United Hebrew Charities of the City of New York, Now the Jewish Social Service Association, Inc. (ca. 1926)
      The Story of the Mount Sinai Hospital: The Formative Years, 1852-1872 (1942)
      The Story of the First Fifty Years of the Mount Sinai Hospital, New York, 1852-1902 (1944)
    - Jewish life and religion (folder 1 of 2), 1818–1918; 201755 (Box 30, Folder 1)
      Mordecai M. Noah, Discourse, Delivered at the Consecration of the Synagogue... (1818)
      S. H. Jackson, ed., The Jew: Being a Defence of Judaism (1824)
      How the Roman Bishops Take Pity on the Jews (1870)
      Max J. Kohler, Rebecca Franks: An American Jewish Belle of the Last Century (1894)
      Constitution and the Rights Appertaining to Members and Rules and Regulations, of the Hebra Hased Va-Amet of the Congregation Shearith Israel (1901)
      Emil Cohn, Some Problems of Modern Jewry (1907)
      Harry Friedenwald, The Attitude of the American Zionist: Two Addresses (1907)
      Maurice Fishberg, The Jews: A Study of Race and Environment (1911)
      Report of the Special Committee of Seven on Religious Educational Societies Made to the Organization Committee of the Federation For the Support of Jewish Philanthropic Societies of New York City (1917)
      David Werner Amram, A Jewish State in Palestine (1918)
      Martin Feinstein, Verses from the Trenches (1918)
      Jewish War Relief 1918 Campaign materials (1918)
    - Jewish life and religion (folder 2 of 2), 1919–1976; 201756 (Box 30, Folder 2)
      M. W. Norwalk, The Economic Basis of the New Jewish State (1919)
      Israel Friedlaender, Zionism and the World Peace (1919)
      Little Studies in Judaism I: Rosh Ha-Shanah and Yom Kippur (1920)
      Federation for the Support of Jewish Philanthropic Societies of New York City, Annual Report of the Treasurer for the Year Ending Dec. 31, 1920 (1921)
      The "Protocols" Bolshevism and the Jews (1920/21)
      NEHILAH OU ENCERRAMENTO DE KIPUR (SEGUNDO O RITO PORTUGUES) (1929)
      [publication in Judaeo-Spanish and Hebrew] (1929)
      Opinion: A Journal of Jewish Life and Letters (21 March 1932)
      Louis Finkelstein, Israel Davidson (1939)
      The Congregation Shearith Israel in the City of New York, Founded 1655 (1940)
      Simon H. Rifkin, The Responsibilities of the Jewish Laity (1949)
      The Jewish Museum, Jewish Experience in the Art of the Twentieth Century (1976)
    - Congressional Record, 1917–1918; 201757 (Box 30, Folder 3)
      Includes issues of 2–9 April 1917 and 3 September 1918.
    - Miscellaneous topics (folder 1 of 2), 1880–1905; 201758 (Box 30, Folder 4)
      P. Lorillard & Co., Puffs of Wisdom (1880)
      Address of the Rt. Rev. Henry C. Potter, D.D., at the Centennial Commemoration Service of Washington's Inauguration... (1889)
      Edward G. Riggs, "Wall Street," Munsey's Magazine, vol. 10 (Oct. 1893-March 1894)
      President McKinley's Last Speech (1901)
      Facts for New York Parents (1901)
      The Raines Law Hotel and the Social Evil (1905)
    - Miscellaneous topics (folder 2 of 2), 1909–1915; 201759 (Box 30, Folder 5)
      The Outlook, vol. 91, no. 11 (13 March 1909)
      David J. Brewer, The Mission of the United States of America in the Cause of Peace (1909)
      Termination of Treaty Between the United States and Russia (1911)
      The Passport Question: Remarks by Louis Marshall, Esq., and Replies of Senator James A. O'Gorman and Senator Elihu Root (1911)
      The Russian Passport Question. Speech of Hon. William Sulzer, of New York, in the House of Representatives (1911)
      Frank Barkley Copley, The Impeachment of President Israels: A Story of War and Peace (1913)
      James E. Martine, Article on Woman Suffrage Introduced in the United States Senate (1915)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1840s-1946; 201760 (Box 31, Folder 1)
    - Newspaper clippings, undated, 201761 (Box 31, Folder 2)
    - Newspaper clippings [RESTRICTED] (2 folders), 1883–1936; 201762 (Box 31, Folder 3-4)